<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A confutation of the Earle of Newcastles reasons for taking under his command and conduct divers popish recusants in the northerne parts; wherein is shewed both the unlawfulnesse, and danger of arming of papists: being a thing of main consequence for all true Protestants to take present and speciall notice of.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E86_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4131</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872609</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872609</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 15:E86[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A confutation of the Earle of Newcastles reasons for taking under his command and conduct divers popish recusants in the northerne parts; wherein is shewed both the unlawfulnesse, and danger of arming of papists: being a thing of main consequence for all true Protestants to take present and speciall notice of.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Overton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 26. 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Newcastle, William Cavendish, --  Duke of, 1592-1676. --  Declaration made by the Earl of New-Castle, Governour of the town and county of New-Castle.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONFVTATION Of the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtles</hi> REASONS For taking under his Command and conduct divers Popiſh Recuſants in the Northerne parts;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN Is ſhewed both the unlawfulneſſe, and danger of Arming of Papiſts:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being a thing of main conſequence for all true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to take preſent and ſpeciall notice of.</p>
            <p>London Printed for <hi>Henry Overton,</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:125052:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125052:2"/>
            <head>A CONFUTATION OF The Earle of Newcaſtles Reaſons, for taking under his Command and Conduct divers Popiſh Recuſants in the Northerne Parts.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a Declaration lately print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under the name of the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> an Earle and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>England,</hi> and by birth and diſcent an Engliſh man, of the Family of <hi>Cavendiſh,</hi> now Generall of an Army in the Northerne parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; Conſiſting moſt part of Papiſts, raiſed, as is conceived, to ſuppreſſe the Liberty of <hi>England,</hi> contrary to the Fundamentall Lawes of the Land; and to eſtabliſh that long excogitated Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:125052:3"/>which evill Counſellours (aſpiring by flattery to become great) have divers yeares ſince projected; Wherein the Author of the Declaration firſt deſires the Subjects of the County of <hi>Yorke,</hi> to take into their ſerious conſideration ſeverall particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and expects credit to be given to them; theſe I paſſe over at this preſent, in hope the good Subjects of that County will in due time make it appeare how little credit is to be given to the Author of that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, who would juſtifie actions ſo contrary to the profeſſions of the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> made to God, to the Church, and to his Countrey. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, He deſires to give ſatisfaction both to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> and all other true Proteſtants of this Kingdome, why hee hath beene neceſſitated to take under his Command and Conduct divers Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Recuſants in the Northerne Parts, alleaging, Firſt, It was not His Majeſties intention, nor the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention (for any thing his Lordſhip knowes) of any in Authority under him, to admit any of them (that is to ſay, Popiſh Recuſants) into that ſervice, if the way had not been chalked out to His Majeſty, and His Miniſters, by the very men, in whoſe Forge the Objection was raiſed. Let (ſaith the Earle) the Muſter Rolls of that Army which is named from the Parliament bee peruſed, and then it ſhall appeare plainly that the mannagers of that Army doe exactly and diſtinctly know, that they now have, and for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moneths have had great numbers under their pay, both Engliſh, French, and other Nations, whom at
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125052:3"/>their Inrollment (and ever ſince) they did know to have been profeſſed Papiſts; Whereas by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, it is notoriouſly knowne, that before this courſe was taken by the other party, His Majeſty and His Miniſters did not admit to, nor continue any Souldiers in pay, who were ſuſpected to be that way inclined, or did refuſe the Oaths of Alleagiance and Supremacy; Not that His Majeſty thought it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for him ſo to doe, or that he did not hold his Recuſant Subjects to be as ſtrongly obliged by the Lawes of this Land, for the defence of His Perſon, and the Liberty of Parliaments, and Lawes of this Kingdome, as any of His Proteſtant Subjects: For if the Kingdome now ſtood under the feare of a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne invaſion; Is it to be conceived that the Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants of this Land were not by the Lawes of the ſame obliged to adventure their lives and fortunes in the defence thereof? Sure the great confuſion which is now in this kingdome, is of as fearefull a conſequence as any Forraigne Invaſion poſſible can bee; and therefore Recuſants are ſo far from being diſobliged, as they ſtand deeply obliged for giving their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in this time of extremity; But His Majeſty was very cautelous, and tender in this point, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly would not have looked towards it, if the other party had not firſt aſſumed that liberty to themſelves, from which by the Law of the Land he ſaw himſelfe no way barred.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the Earle, or who elſe is the Author of that Declaration under his name, takes upon him to be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125052:4"/>to his Majeſties intentions, and to excuſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Miniſters concerning the arming of Popiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants, it were earneſtly to bee wiſhed that men would not withhold the truth with unrighteouſneſſe, nor goe about to deceive the world with Colours. Let the Author declare who chalked the way to His Majeſties Counſellors and Miniſters, to adviſe and procure His Majeſtie to recommend, if not authoriſe <hi>Randoll Mac donell,</hi> now Earle of <hi>Antrim,</hi> a Papiſt (and by diſcent meere Iriſh, being the Grandſon to <hi>Sorley boy mac donell</hi> by the Fathers ſide, and of the moſt perfidious Traytor and enemy of the truth, <hi>Hugh Oneale,</hi> Earle of Tirone, by the Mothers ſide, who alſo was one of the Conſpirators of the preſent Rebellion in Ireland, and yet is harboured about Newcaſtle, or Durham) to raiſe an Army in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, with which he being Generall, ſhould invade the kingdome of <hi>Scotland;</hi> a deſigne, though croſſed, more through emulation and envy, then for any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to his Majeſties Honour, or conſcience to afflict a Proteſtant Church and Nation by an Army of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, diſcovereth plainly that there hath been an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to admit Papiſts to ſerve under His Majeſtie, for the deſtruction of ſome of his Proteſtant Subjects before ſuch a ſuppoſed chalking out of the way, as the Author of this Declaration pretends, as may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be evidenced by the bringing of 500. Souldiers out of Ireland to Carlile, a part (if not the greateſt) of that number being Papiſts, and the many Popiſh Commanders, Captaines, Officers, and Souldiers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:125052:4"/>entertained and imployed in the two Northerne Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditions againſt <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the latter of which, <hi>Garret Barry,</hi> now Lieutenant Generall of the Rebels Army in the Province of <hi>Munſter</hi> in Ireland, ſerved; having quit his places held under the King of Spaine, to come into <hi>England</hi> for an employment in that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition; another <hi>Barry</hi> alſo, a Papiſt much cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant at the Court, was Serjeant Major of a Regiment of Horſe, Colonell <hi>Plunket,</hi> now in Rebellion in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Colonell <hi>Rely,</hi> an Iriſh man, with very many other Papiſts of Ireland, were enabled by the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment they received in <hi>England</hi> in thoſe Northerne Expeditions, to doe no ſmall miſchiefe ſince to the Proteſtants, beſides many others of Forraigne Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with our owne well knowne Country men of the Popiſt Religion; Witneſſe likewiſe the Army raiſed in Ireland in the beginning of the yeare 1640. in a manner conſiſting of Papiſts altogether, ſave that the chiefe Officers of the Field, and divers other Officers and Souldiers were Proteſtants, that kingdome at that time not affording men of the Popiſh Religion, having Military abilities to diſcharge the duties of ſo great places, but nothing wanted to let them know how much they were relyed upon: Sir <hi>Tobie Mathews</hi> a Jeſuit, attended upon the Earle of <hi>Strafford</hi> into Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land in March, before the raiſing of that Army, and during his abode there, was lodged in his Lordſhips houſe of reſidence, the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and every day rid upon one of Sir <hi>George Radcliffs</hi> horſes to one or other of the publique Maſſe-houſes in <hi>Dublin,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:125052:5"/>where Sir <hi>Tobie</hi> conſulted often and ſeriouſly with Prelates and other Eccleſiaſticall perſons of the Church of Rome, by whom he prepared the partie of Papiſts in the Parliament of Ireland then ſitting, to aſſent to a Declaration againſt the kingdome of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and to grant more Subſidies to advance that war then they have yet paid: But to come neerer home to the writer of the Declaration, hath the Parliament or his Exeelencie the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> given Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or power to any Colonell, or Commander of the Popiſh Religion to levie, conduct, and command Regiments, Troopes, or Bands of men in the preſent ſervice? As the Earle of Newcaſtle, his Majeſties Generall in the Northern parts hath done; Are there whole Regiments, or Companies, conſiſting all, or moſt part of Papiſts (exactly and diſtinctly knowne by the Parliament to be ſuch) admitted to ſerve un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or any other Commander in Chiefe imployed by the Parliament? Surelie none. But ſuch are in great eſteeme and credit, and much truſted in the ſeverall Armies latelie raiſed, and now on foote by vertue of ſeverall Commiſſions granted by his Maieſtie to the Earle of Newcaſtle and others, to defend the Proteſtant Religion, the Lawes of this kingdome (by which Papiſts are declared unfit to bee truſted with Armes) and the Libertie of the Subject, as is pretended: Now admitting ſome Papiſts have through negligence, or by friendſhip with private Captaines, or other Officers, got into the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Army (as it may be ſuppoſed ſome have done
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:125052:5"/>of purpoſe to betray the Counſells and deſignes of that Armie) is that a good juſtification for exciting and authorizing all the Papiſts in the North and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places fit to beare Armes, to take up Armes for for the deſtruction of the Proteſtants and ſuppreſſion of Religion, Lawes, and Liberties eſtabliſhed in the Land? The Author of the ſaid Declaration glanceth at the Proclamation lately publiſhed, prohibiting all Popiſh Recuſants to come to his Majeſties Court, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they would take the Oaths of Allegiance and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie; ſtricter Proclamations againſt Papiſts have beene freequent heretofore, yet they never affrighted the Papiſts, who were well acquainted with the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Adviſors of ſuch Proclamations: It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Hiſtory that a Chriſtian Emperour having under hand waged a great Armie to warre upon the Pope, cauſed the Citie of <hi>Rome</hi> to be ſackt, and the Pope to be beſieged in the Caſtle of Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> yet when the tidings thereof became publike and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in all countries; he ordained a Faſt to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in his Court for the ſafety and delivery of the Pope; an impious diſſimulation, and ſuch as ſhould not be imitated by any Prince Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>But it muſt be acknowledged that the Author of the Declaration aforeſaid, dealeth more plainely then the Pen-men of his Majeſties Declarations uſually doe, for he affirmeth that his Majeſtie thinkes it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for him to admit into his ſervice, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in pay profeſſed Papiſts, and that his Majeſtie doth hold his Recuſant ſubjects (meaning Papiſts)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:125052:6"/>to be as ſtrongly obliged by the Lawes of the Land, for the defence of his perſon, and the liberty of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, and Lawes of the Kingdome, as any of his Proteſtant Subjects, &amp;c. whether his Majeſtie will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow the ſame or no is yet unknowne, therefore till time diſcover it, let the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> or who elſe publiſhed the ſaid Declaration under his name, be favourably pleaſed to underſtand, that although all Subjects be alike obliged by Law for defence of their Soveraignes perſon, and the liberties and Lawes of the Kingdome, yet all Subjects have not the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the liberties and Laws of the Kingdome now in force; neither did any Papiſt ever affirme, that he affects the liberty of the Parliaments as Proteſtants doe, which his Majeſtie knowes well by their cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and inſinuation at all times to bring him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like with Parliaments, if it were poſſible: And albeit his Majeſtie may be conſtrued to be exempt from the Excommunication of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> againſt the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe hee was not borne in <hi>England,</hi> yet when the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> or any of his Majeſties Children ſhall ſucceede in the Royall Throne, they may be accounted Excommunicate, and if the Pope doe at any time hereafter enjoyne the Papiſt to deny Alleagiance to his Majeſtie by colour of that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, or ſome other Romane device, may finde as little fidelity in the Papiſts, as Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> did, and they will never conceive themſelves ſo obliged as is ſet forth in the ſaid Declaration, in regard they held a ſupremacie in the Pope above the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:125052:6"/>
               <hi>King</hi> in matters Eccleſiaſticall, which at this time are become not the leaſt occaſions of the apparent evills, and threatned ruine ready to fall upon his Majeſties Dominions; nor doth the taking of the Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie ſecure their alleagiance or fidelitie to the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> being Proteſtants, conſidering there is a power admitted by them to be in the <hi>Pope</hi> to diſpence with Oathes, in matters leſſe conducing to the advancement of the Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchie, then to diſſemble in taking the Oath of Supremacie, as teſtifieth the Example of Cardinall <hi>Askanius,</hi> who being releaſed out of priſon by the <hi>French King,</hi> and after great kindneſſes received in that <hi>Kingdome,</hi> was permitted to goe to <hi>Rome</hi> with the Cardinall <hi>D' Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boiſe</hi> to be at the election of a <hi>Pope,</hi> to ſucceede <hi>Pope Alexander,</hi> tooke an Oath that he would returne to <hi>France</hi> againe, yet refuſed ſo to doe, having obtained the <hi>Popes</hi> diſpenſation to breake his faith with the Chriſtian <hi>King,</hi> which a Heathen <hi>Romane</hi> of old would not doe to eſcape the moſt grievous torments; the matter then ſtanding thus, and the Law of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land not allowing that Papiſts ſhould have Armes, although the <hi>King</hi> may diſpence with the Law in ſome caſes, for the good and tranquility of the people, yet in this caſe, where one of the pretences for Arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the defence of the Proteſtant Religion, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother pretence is the maintenance of priviledges of Parliament; Why is not his Majeſty barred by the equity and intent of the Law from admitting Papiſts into the preſent ſervice? Seeing all papiſts are taught
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:125052:7"/>to have both the proteſtant Religion, &amp; the parliament more then any Religion or Court of Juſtice in the world, and therefore cannot be conceived by any of mean underſtanding, much leſſe by the Earle of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle,</hi> to ſtand neither ſo deeply obliged, nor ſo well affected to defend either the <hi>Kings</hi> perſon, being a proteſtant, or the proteſtant Religion, or priviledges of parliament, as the proteſtant Subjects of England are.</p>
            <p>The Author of the aforſaid declaration poceedeth to examyne the pretended in conveniences where with the arming of papiſts is alleadged to be attended, &amp; in the firſt place voucheth for iuſtification of the uniuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable arming of papiſts, the example of the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, who being a Popiſh Emperor did not refuſe the ſervice of any of the Proteſtants of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many in that Army wherewith he made warre upon the Proteſtants; Secondly, he citeth the example of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, the late French King, while he was a Proteſtant, and did not reiect the aſſiſtance of the french Papiſts that adhered to him, and laſtly the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the States of the united Provinces, who doe not reiect the auxiliary Regiments under the pay of the french <hi>King,</hi> becauſe many of them (if not moſt) are papiſts: how farre remote theſe examples are from the preſent caſe, let all indifferent men judge: the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth warred upon the proteſtants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were proteſtants, and if in that caſe he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted proteſtants to ſerve under him, and imployed them in ſuppreſſing and deſtroying their brethren,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:125052:7"/>we will blame his policie, and if at this day the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Wars of England were waged by his Majeſty, to reſtraine the inſolencies and practiſes of the papiſts (who doubtleſſe intend the like cruelties in England, as have been acted againſt the proteſtants in Ireland) who would thinke amiſſe of admitting papiſts to fight againſt papiſts, as in the Civill Wars of Ireland in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Raigne; moreover all the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſerving in the Army raiſed by the parliament, rare, and ever will be ready to ſpend their lives in defence of his Majeſties perſon, and deſire nothing but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Laws to be ſecured againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall plots and practiſes of the Papiſts, to ſubvert this Noble Kingdome, and eſtabliſh the Articles of the Antichriſtian Counſell of Trent therein, which may be the more eaſily effected by them, if once His Majeſty ſhall be ſo far ſeduced by evill Counſell, as to continue them in Armies againſt his Parliament, upon pretence of jealouſies, and ſuſpitions of diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to his Royall perſon, a thing far below the thoughts of any Proteſtant, much more of the high Court of Parliament, who have in ſo many Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions called God to witneſſe the integrity of their hearts, to ayme at nothing but the glory and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Majeſty, and the preſervation of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhip without mixture of Idolatry, ſuperſtition, or error: As to the example of the late French King, was not his Succeſſion and Coronation oppoſed by the Guiſes, and the Pope? Only becauſe he was an Hugonite (as they terme all Proteſtants in France)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:125052:8"/>had he in any thing violated the Laws of the Realme when the holy League was made up to exclude him from poſſeſſing his royall Throne, or was be ever ſaid to ſuffer evill Counſellors to goe about, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to introduce other Government then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Government of the Kingdome? Although theſe had not been cauſes ſufficient, yet was there not the leaſt of theſe pretended, what wonder was it then, if French papiſts adhered to their rightfull and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Succeſſor of the Crowne of France, and he ſhould uſe their ſervice againſt their fellow papiſts, who would ſet up Tyrants to rule againſt Law and good Conſcience: This example therefore may not ſerve for juſtifying the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtles</hi> arming of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts at this time, no more then the other example of the States of Holland to admit the auxiliary Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of French men, ſome of whom may be, and are papiſts, nay ſuppoſing they were all papiſts, the Chriſtian world ſeeth manifeſtly they may bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the Wars againſt the Spaniard, it is but pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt againſt papiſt ſtill, it is not againſt the proteſtants thoſe French auxiliaries are imployed, neither are they made uſe of to hinder the eſtabliſhing and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the proteſtant Religion: Let then all Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that are not papiſts, be well adviſed, leſt any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinnent arguments divide them, but in all loyall dutifulneſſe continue in unity, and endeavour to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the peace of the Land, aad defend each others perſons and eſtates againſt thoſe enemies of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion &amp; Laws, now armed by the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:125052:8"/>and beare the reproaches of ſuch men patiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Almighty, who ruleth the hearts of Kings, crowne the religious endeavours of thoſe that ſeeke not their owne, but the glory of God, and his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, with bleſſings of peace, unity, and love in the fruition of his Majeſties royall favour and concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, to ſettle the diſtracted and diſtreſſed condition of this moſt noble and potent Kingdome, and of poore Ireland now ſowed thicke with the bodies of Martyrs, whoſe blood will doubtleſſe produce a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull harveſt of living Saints, through the mighty power of him that propagated his Goſpell into all Lands, maugre all worldly power and policy that oppoſed it, I ſay no more, accounting the inferences of the Declarator unworthy of anſwer, but conclude with the Pſalmiſt,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 129. Ver. 5, 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Let them all be confounded and turned backe that hate Zion.</l>
               <l>Let them be as graſſe upon the houſe top, which wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth afore it groweth up.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
